side welcome back and today in this
event-driven architecture we are going
to start with Kafka. So before we start
implementing or using Kafka like how to
publish an event, how to consume an
event, we first need to understand how
Kafka works and I will just take 2
minutes to set up a context so that you
can get to know what you can expect from
this total uh parts of this uh Kafka
architecture. So this is not going to be
like 15 20 minutes highle overview of
Kafka. So I'm trying my best to cover as
much as I can and in depth of Kafka.
Okay. So at any point of time you feel
that it's getting complex kindly pause
the video okay and clear those things
out and then proceed further because
this is critical and very very important
topic. So let's start it.
So in event-driven architecture
introduction part we have already seen
what is pubsub model what is streaming
model the difference and advantages of
ED. So today we're going to start with
most popular streaming model streaming
model I'm saying Kafka.
Okay. The first very important interview
question itself like what is Kafka?
very very like with to me also this
question has been asked a lot what is
Kafka okay so we have to explain like
it's a distributed
event streaming platform
okay and from the previous video you
might have already know what does
streaming means so streaming means
we can store the events okay so we can
replay later also so it's a distributed
event streaming platform that allow us
to publish an event, store the event,
subscribe to the events like you can
consume those events also consume
events.
Okay.
Now let's uh see
components of Kafka you can say that.
Okay. The first very important part is
producer.
Producer is an application that
publishes event to Kafka. So you have a
producer, you are publishing an event to
Kafka. Producer doesn't care who will
consume this event. Okay? It doesn't
care about the consumer part. That's
what I mean to say. Okay? So very simple
producer. Okay? and things I will keep
on adding more and more and more info
but I am going like you can say that uh
in a simple to complex manner.
The second very important part is topic.
So consider topic as category or folder
to which events are published. So see
category do not holds the event. No, it
is just a folder or you can say that a
category uh you are creating so that uh
or you can say logical grouping of
events. So in this case let's say I have
a producer one producer two and I have
created one topic order events.
So now any events I publish I can
producer one can say that hey publish
this event to this topic. Okay. So
consider topic as a folder
which stores the events.
Okay. So it's a
category and you can say that it's a
logical concept. Okay.
Many producer can write to same topic.
Like very simple.
Then very very important partition
a physical check this line a physical
ordered and append only log that is part
of a topic a topic can have many
partition.
So producer here if you see we have a
topic
within a topic we can have multiple
partition partition zero partition one
partition two now what is this partition
so I mentioned it's a physical physical
means
events are actually stored on disk
inside the partition okay so partitions
are the one which actually stored the
events. So here if you see I have a
folder let's say order events. So this
folder is nothing but a topic. Now
within this [snorts]
I have partition zero, partition one,
partition two. Okay, order - events 0.
Let's say this is the naming for the
partition zero. It has one log file.
Similarly, partition one has one log
file. Partition two has one log file.
Okay. So these are the partitions is one
thing is physical means they are the one
that actually stored the logs or events
on disk. Okay.
The second is ordered.
What does ordered mean? Events are
returned sequentially
and assign increment offset.
So here if you see when producer publish
an event let's say event zero so event
zero let's say goes to the partition
zero okay so whenever any event comes to
a partition partition assign one offset
to it okay it generates an increment
offset let's say offset is already used
till 80 so it will generate the next
offset let's say 81 and whatever the new
event is coming it will append this
information with it. So now let's say
event zero offset one is assigned event
one let's say goes to the partition one
we will see that it goes to the
partition one offset one is assigned and
event two goes to the partition two
offset one is assigned okay so each
partition maintains their own offset
list okay independently
so now let's say in partition zero the
next event comes event three. So what it
will do is it will check its counter
increment counter. It will check what's
the next offset two. So it will this
event is
attached with this offset offset two.
Don't worry about like hey why we are
creating multiple partition what is the
purpose? Don't worry about this for at
this point of time. My moto is that you
are familiar with this terms topic. What
is topic? What is producer? What is
partition? Because slowly we are going
to go more in depth. So at by that time
this naming should be clear. Okay.
So partition is physical means actual
data is stored here on disk.
It's ordered. Whatever the file let's
say this partition lock file whatever
the file it is creating it's properly
ordered. So the first entry is let's say
for offset zero then second entry is for
offset one offset two offset three. So
event zero event one event two whatever.
So in this particular partition whatever
events are going it's are properly order
in an offset manner. Okay. So every
event comes to a particular partition,
it will generate a new offset in
increment order and append the offset
with that particular event. Okay.
Also consumer read them in offset order.
So consumer can't say that hey give me
let's say then 32 then 42 then 52. No
consumer will say that hey give me let's
say I need to read the events from
offset 100 to 200. So it's always in a
sequential manner. Okay. 100 10 100 101
102 like this.
Each partition maintain its next offset
counter. So each partition maintains
their independent offset counters. Okay?
It's not like offset one here. Then it
can only have offset two here. No. So
partition zero maintain its own offset.
Offset one, offset two, offset three.
Similarly, partition different other
partition also maintain their own
offsets. Offset one, offset two, offset
three. Okay.
When new event arrives, Kafka assign new
offset to that event and append the
event to the log.
Within a single partition, order is
guaranteed. Very important. Within a
single partition, order is guaranteed.
What does that mean? Means events are
written sequentially and read in
increasing offset manner.
So order is guaranteed. Let's say
partition zero.
Event zero comes here. So it store event
zero with offset let's say one. Then
event one comes. So it append the file.
So in so all this data goes within a
file and in the file it just append
only. So this event is assigned next
offset offset two. Okay. So always in
increment order. So within a one
partition order is guaranteed. So you
can easily says that
event one happens after event zero.
Okay. Because event zero has come first
that's why it has offset one and event
one happens later after event zero
that's why it has offset two. Okay. So
order is maintained within a single
partition.
But it does not guarantee order globally
like globally I mean say partition zero
partition one partition two you can't
predict the order.
So that's the same example I give here
that in partition zero itself we know
that event three here event three
happened after event zero because offset
two comes after offset one in the
partition. So if you just look at this
partition you can know the ordering that
event three happens after event zero
because its offset is higher than this.
But I cannot guarantee that event four
which is there in partition one. So
event four is there. I cannot guarantee
that this event four happened either
before or after let's say event zero
which is in different partition
because they both are independent
counters right they're both maintaining
their counters independently. So I can't
guarantee that this event four which is
at offset two is happen after or before
event zero which is at offset one but in
different partition I cannot guarantee
that
okay
so these are the second property or you
can say that the partition that it's a
physical ordered and append only log. Uh
now what does append only? So now say
that this is the current scenario. So
for this topic order events it has three
partition and currently the partition
holds this information. So we know that
it's the actual physical uh where the uh
data is stored on the disk on files.
Okay. So this is my order events
considered as a folder. Then I have one
partition zero file, partition one log
file, partition two log file. And this
is the current uh let's say the file
data. Okay. So partition zero has event
zero, event three information. Okay.
Event zero has at offset one. Event
three currently stored at offset two.
Similarly, partition one has event one,
event four information. and partition
two has event two information.
Now let's say new event arrive at E5 at
partition P2 E5 here. So if you see that
E5 is added what partition two will do?
It will compute the new offset. So new
offset would be after offset one offset
two will come and it will append. So in
its file partition two in its log file
it appends
the new event offset to event five
record. Okay. So foil is always file is
always appended. It's
okay.
Now at this point of time
we have one little highle information
about partition.
But let me go one level more deeper into
this.
This partition log file is further
divided into segments.
Okay. So understand this. We have a
topic which is nothing but a folder.
Then we have partition zero. Let's say
this partition. I'm focusing uh double
clicking on this partition. Earlier at
this point of time our understanding is
partition zero has one file log file but
what I am saying is that even the
partition instead of having one big log
file it broken into multiple segments
okay so this is my partition zero
ordered event hyphen 0 now here if you
see within this I have multiple segment
segment one segment two segment three
multiple segments small small small
segments. So these segment log files
actually holds the data. Okay. So let's
say this segment has named 000000.log.
So generally what it says that this
segment is store event with offset
starting from zero. Okay. Now let the
next segment is segment two. Let's say
it naming is 0000 500. So means this
segment is store event
with offset starting from 500. So means
the previous one started from zero and
end till 499. So this segment is store
all the events with offset from 0 to
499.
This segment is store all events which
is starting from 500 till we can get to
know that the third segment is 1,000.
So store event with offset is starting
from 1,000. So means it has till 999 the
previous one and this is let's say
ongoing there is no more. So this is an
ongoing offsets is there.
So segment uh naming convention is like
this itself. So in the name uh itself
you can determine that it is starting
from which offset events are started
with which offset.
Why you can ask right why? First of all,
why we are dividing one log file into
multiple segment files?
Because consumer in Kafka can say that
hey I want to read from partition zero
partition zero
from offset 550 to 800. Now if you have
a one big log file
okay and I told you that it's
sequential. This file is sequential
offset one offset two like this. So
if you have only one big file then
reading those file loading that file in
the memory takes time okay and it's not
efficient. Now if consumer says that hey
I want to read from 550 to 800. One good
advantage here is that based on the
segment itself, Kafka can directly jump
to a specific segment itself.
Okay. So this segment it knows that it
stores this
offset range. Okay. So it will load only
this in the memory.
Okay.
That's the first advantage. Our
searching can little bit faster.
And also we can control the segment size
too. Say if I want to keep the segment
size as 1 GB then again sequential
search in 1GB segment file will also
take time. So this is another challenge.
We can give the size of the segment.
Okay. Like I want to keep the segment
each segment size as 1 GB. 1 GB 1 GB
Now what I told you that
okay user wants to
do a lookup for 550 to 800 user wants to
uh consumer wants to consume this event
[snorts]
okay with offset 550 to 800 and we know
that uh using this segment Kafka a
directly able to jump to a particular
segment
now this segment is still 1 GB be big.
Okay. And it has a lot of entries.
Assume
again iterating over this [snorts]
little bit slow. Can we make it little
bit more faster? Yes, Kafka does it. How
it maintains an index file also with it.
So again
order event just a topic. Consider a
folder. We have a partition zero.
Currently uh double clicking on one
partition. Now this partition can have
multiple segments. So I'm just now
double clicking on one segment. Let's
say segment one 000000.log.
What does it mean? This segment stores
event with offset starting from zero.
Okay.
Now this also maintains
index file also. So if you see this, let
me zoom it a bit. This index file is
store information like this offset zero
physical position in the log file. This
segment has log file right. So index
zero you can find at zero.
Index 150 you can find it 4,200 bytes.
Offset 300 you will find out this memory
position.
Offset 450 you can find at this
position. So here you notice that one
thing is in the index
it stores
not every
offset details like okay offset zero at
this position offset one offset two
offset no otherwise your index file
would become too big. So it stores so we
can also control this. Okay. So there is
a way through which we can tell that
after how many bytes you want to store
one index entry.
Okay, I will show you an example. But
with this index file
we can easily know that okay
user is asking for 550 right let's say
offset. So 450 at present here. So means
or let's say if there is no more so at
least it will start from this position
start looking okay. So it make the
search little bit more faster within the
segment also. So two level of you can
say that efficiency. One is uh it can
directly goes to a specific chunk
directly go to that particular segment
which hosts that particular offset range
and within that segment file it can make
use of index segment index file and it
directly
goes to a you can say the nearest or
exact depending upon what info we have
in the index file. it goes to the
nearest memory position and start look
up from there.
Okay, that's what I written here. Not
every offset is indexed. Instead, it
index every n bytes. We can configure
that one. Means after n bytes have been
returned to lock file, it create one
index row. This saves memory and also
helps in faster lookup.
Example, consider this example. Things
will get a little bit more clear.
partition zero let's say offset zero
event size is 300 bytes offset one
offset two offset three so this
holds information in log okay so these
many bytes are there so offset zero is
of 300 bytes offset one 500 bytes offset
two whatever the record we have is 1,000
bytes of offset three offset four like
this and you have configured that
segment size should be 1 GB
and index interval byte is 4096 bytes.
So this you have configured. Okay. After
this many bytes
you need to create one entry into this
index record.
So how will happen? So now let's say
this is nothing but a folder the topic.
Now this topic we are talking about
partition zero.
This partition can have multiple
segments. So we are dealing with only
currently one segment. Let's say
0000.log
store events with offset starting from
zero. So now first event come offset
zero event size is 300 byt. So consider
that this is how the data goes into the
file. Offset zero
event size is 300 bytes. File position
currently at zero. Okay. The next offset
one, this one event size is 500 byte,
its file position is starting 300
because the first one is 300. So that
finishes off after that it will start.
Okay. Similarly, offset two, the record
at offset 2 is of,000 bytes and it is
starting is 800. This 300 is uh of uh
event zero
and then 500 is your event one.
So now your event two which is at offset
two is starting from this 800.
Okay.
Similarly at offset three you have
another event which is of 2,000 bytes.
Okay. And its file position is starting
from is that from 18800 it is starting.
Okay. And offset four this. Now you have
stored this into dot log file. The total
bite return is 300 + 500 +,000 + 2,000 +
500 4,300 bytes has been returned to the
log. And what you have configured here
index interval bytes is 4096 byt. Okay.
So now the bytes you have written in the
log is greater than this many bytes you
have configured. So means it will insert
one entry into the index that last one.
Hey
offset four
physical position here is 3800.
Got it?
So
now one question might be coming to your
mind is that okay this things got clear
but how producer decide that
okay producer is publishing an event
let's say event zero event one event two
how producer decide that hey this event
should goes to partition zero this event
should go to partition one this event
should go to partition two how it decide
So there are certain algorithms for it.
The first algorithm is key based
partitioning.
All events for same key will goes to the
same partition. So now let's say this is
the publisher
publish message.
The first is like topic in which topic
publisher want to publish this event.
It also has a key. Okay. Based on this
key, it will decide it will goes to
which partition and ultimate the record
event. Okay. So now what it will do is
it compute a hash hash of order ID hash
of this key
and modulo of number of partition we
have. So currently we have three
partitions. So let's say hash of 1 2 3
your key is 1 2 3 mod 3 it goes to the
partition one event zero event 1 has ID
456 so hash of 456 mod 3 you got
partition two so event one goes to
partition two similarly event two got
partition zero so it goes here so that
is one way another way is roundroin that
during publish
you don't provide a key. So what
internally Kafka will do is it follow a
round robin. Hey, you want to publish
into this topic. Okay. And I have three
partition. Let me do a roundroin. Event
zero goes to partition zero. Event one
goes to partition one. Event two goes to
partition two. And then after that again
partition zero next event. So it's a
round robin.
And another is custom partitioning. like
you can decide that okay if country is
India goes to the partition zero if
country is US goes to the partition one
that is also possible okay so we can
write those custom partitioning logic
and when we will try to implement uh or
use Kafka in our code we can use this
scenario how to write a custom
partitioning
okay so partitioning I think now we have
a better understanding. So we have done
producer.
What is producer? What is topic? What is
partition and it's different
like uh segments
index file in this one. So subp parts of
it should be clear.
Now we have broker.
What is broker? Broker is a single Kafka
server instance.
A broker is one which actually stores
data and serves client. So you can say
that it is actually the server.
Okay. So with this diagram it become
clear that you have a producer. We know
that we have a topic we have a partition
but they should it's again an
application at the end. So they should
also have a server right. So that server
in which this partition are running you
can say that it's known as Kafka broker.
So it's actually a server Kafka server.
Okay. So broker stores some partition of
some topic. Very very important. Okay.
At this point of time you will find this
line little complicate.
Okay. A broker stores some partition of
some topic.
See in Kafka you can have multiple
topics. Let's say topic one
order events. So this
topic all the order related events goes
to this topic. You can have another
topic let's say sales event.
You can have another topic. Let's say
product events.
Okay. And each topic we know that can
have multiple partition. Partition zero,
partition one, partition two. It can
have two partition. Partition zero,
partition one. It can have again three
partition. Partition zero, partition
one, partition two.
So what this line means that a broker
stores some partition of some topic. So
one broker one Kafka server do not hold
all this information. It do not hold all
the topic
and also whatever the topic it holds. It
do not holds all the partition also.
So you might be thinking then what about
the topics or what about the partition
which this Kafka broker do not stores
where those will be stored I will come
to that later when we discuss about
Kafka cluster
but at this point of time all I want is
that you understand Kafka broker is that
[snorts] it's a one single instance of
Kafka server okay and it store
some topic and some partitions.
Okay, it do not store like complete all
topics whatever we have and for each
topic all partition or it's not like
let's say topic one it have so it also
need to have its all partition no it
holds some topic some partition
and that's why I have put into important
note topics and partition are
distributed across multiple brokers I
told you that multiple broker part I
don't want to bring that term now
because I will discuss it when we will
talk about cluster.
Okay.
So that part is clear
broker part. Okay. Now we have consumer
and consumer group and I will discuss
that into part two.
Okay. I told you that I will go a little
slow and in uh parts because
things are going to get more complicated
into consumer and consumer groups also.
Okay. So, see you in the part two and if
you have any doubt in the part one, let
me know. We can discuss into the comment
section. Bye.